When the Kundalini rises
Kundalini yükseldiği zaman,
it makes sounds.
bu sesler çıkarır
And the sounds that are heard
ve farklı çakralarda duyulan seslerde,
in the different chakras can be pronounced
şu şekilde telaffuz edilebilir
in the following way –
- bu telaffuzlar
these pronunciations are being used
'Devaların konuştuğu dil' anlamına gelen
in the phonetic language of Devanagari,
Devanagari’nin fonetik
which means ‘the language spoken by the Devas’.
dilinde kullanılmaktadır.
At the Mooladhara,
Dört taç yaprağı olan
where there are four petals,
Mooladhara'daki sesler şunlardır:
the sounds are: [vum, shum, sshum, sum].
[vum, shum, sshum, sum].
Out of which the lasts, sshum and sum
Bunlardan sonda olan,
sounds are very close,
shum ve sum sesleri birbirine çok yakındır,
but the difference is – when the snake hisses
ancak aradaki fark şudur: yılan tısladığı zaman,
it makes this sshum – the third sound.
üçüncü ses olan, bu shum sesini çıkarır.
So, vum, shum, sshum, sum.
Yani, vum, shum, sshum, sum.
At the Swadishthana, where there are six petals,
Swadishthana'da,altı taç yaprağın olduğu yerde,
it makes sounds, six sounds:
o şu sesleri çıkarır, altı tane ses:
[bum, bhum, mum, yum, rum, lum].
[bum, bhum, mum, yum, rum, lum].
Manipur it has ten petals.
Manipur'da on taç yaprak vardır.
It makes the sounds dum, dhum,
Dum, dhum, num, tum, thum, dum,
num, tum, thum, dum, dhum, nnum, pum, phum.
dhum, nnum, pum, phum seslerini çıkarır.
At Anahata there are twelve petals.
Anahata'da on iki taç yaprak vardır.
It makes the sounds
Şu sesleri çıkarır,
kum, khum, gum, ghum, [ngum-?],
kum, khum, gum, ghum, [ngum-?],
chum, chhum, jum, jhum, [nngum-?], tum, thum.
chum, chhum, jum, jhum, [nngum-?], tum, thum.
At the Vishuddhi, where there are sixteen petals,
On altı taç yaprağının bulunduğu Vishuddhi'de,
it makes the sounds of all the vowels:
o tüm sesli harflerin seslerini çıkarır:
a, aa, i, ii,
a, aa, i, ii,
u, uu, r, rr, lr, lrr, e, ai, o, ou, am, ahm.
u, uu, r, rr, lr, lrr, e, ai, o, ou, am, ahm.
At the Agnya chakra it makes ha, ksha.
Agnya çakrada bu, ha, ksha sesini yapar.
At the Sahasrara, one becomes
Sahasrara'da kişi düşüncesiz hale gelir
thoughtless, and no sound is made.
ve hiç ses çıkmaz.
But the pure Anahata,
Ama saf Anahata, yani kalpte de olduğu gibi,
meaning the throbbing in the purest form
en saf halindeki zonklamaların hepsi:
as in the heart is all: lub-dub, lub-dub, lub-dub.
lub-dub, lub-dub, lub-dub.
When all these sounds are sounded together
Tüm bu sesler birlikte duyulduğu
and pass through the spiral of the body,
ve bedenin spiralinden geçtiği zaman,
if the body is like a conch,
eğer beden bir deniz kabuğu gibiyse,
the sound that comes out of the synthesis is Aum.
sentezden çıkan ses Aum'dur.
Like the seven colors of the sun
Güneşin yedi renginin nihayetinde
ultimately become white rays,
beyaz renkte ışınlara dönüşmesi gibi,
or you can say the golden colored rays.
ya da siz buna altın renkli ışınlar da diyebilirsiniz.
There are three Granthis, means the knots:
Üç Granthi vardır, yani bu isim düğümler anlamına gelir:
the Brahmagranthi,
Brahmagranthi,
the Vishnugranthi and the Rudragranthi.
Vishnugranthi ve Rudragranthi.
With Agni, means fire,
Ateş anlamına gelen Agni ile
when the Brahmagranthi meets between the Kundalini,
Brahmagranthi - Kundalini,
Mooladhara chakra and the Swadishthana –
Mooladhara çakra ve Swadishthana arasında buluştuğunda
means Mooladhara chakra, Mooladhara  and Swadishthana chakra –
- Mooladhara çakra, yani bu Mooladhara ve Swadishthana çakra anlamına gelir
then Agni Brahmagranthi is established.
- o zaman Agni, Brahmagranthi’yi oturtur.
Vishnugranthi when mixes up with the Surya,
Vishnugranthi, Surya ile karıştığında,
that is between the Nabhi and the Ruddhaya chakra,
yani bu Nabhi ve Ruddhaya çakra arasında bulunur,
Surya Vishnugranthi is established.
Surya Vishnugranthi oluşur.
When Vishuddhi and Agnya auras
Vishuddhi ve Agnya auraları bir araya geldiğinde,
meet, then Chandra Rudragranthi is established.
Chandra Rudragranthi oluşur.
Altogether there are fourteen Nadis.
Toplamda on dört tane Nadi vardır.
The names are: Alambusi,
İsimleri, Alambusi,
Kuhu, Vishvodhari, Varuna, Hastajihva,
Kuhu, Vishvodhari, Varuna, Hastajihva,
Yashaswati, Ashvini, Gandhari, Pusha, Shankhini,
Yashaswati, Ashvini, Gandhari, Pusha, Shankhini,
Saraswati, Ida, Pingala, Sushumna.
Saraswati, Ida, Pingala, Sushumna.
Apart from two chakras,
Surya ve Chandra olan iki çakranın dışında
which are Surya and Chandra, there are nine other chakras:
dokuz çakra daha vardır:
Mooladhar chakra, Swadishthan chakra,
Mooladhar çakra, Swadishthan çakra,
Manipur chakra, Anahata chakra,
Manipur çakra, Anahata çakra,
Vishuddhi chakra.
Vishuddhi çakra.
Lambika chakra – this is also called as Hamsaha chakra,
Lambika çakra - buna Hamsaha çakra,
Agnya chakra.
Agnya çakra da denir.
Between Agnya and Sahasrara there are two other sub-chakras,
Agnya ve Sahasrara arasında Naad, Bindu olarak bilinen
known as Naad, Bindu.
iki alt çakra daha vardır.
So, we have: Mooladhara, Swadishthan, Manipur, Anahat,
Yani, elimizde: Mooladhara, Swadishthan, Manipur, Anahat
Vishuddhi, Lambika, called as Sohum – called as Hamsa,
Vishuddhi, Lambika, bu Sohum olarak adlandırılır – Hamsa olarak adlandırılır,
Agnya, Naad, Bindu, Sahasrara.
Agnya, Naad, Bindu, Sahasrara olarak adlandırılır.
Apart from that, there are nine chakras on the sides,
Bunun dışında, Shri Lalita gibi
like Shri Lalita.
yanlarda olan dokuz tane çakra vardır.
And they have different yoginya, yoginis,
Ve bu dokuz Shakti Pitha'ya rehberlik eden farklı yoginya’lar,
means the powers, the Shaktis,
yoginiler, yani güçler,
guiding those nine Shakti Pithas,
Shaktiler vardır ya da siz bunlara
or you can call them as Avarana chakras.
Avarana (gizlemek, bir şeyi sarmak veya örtmek) çakraları da diyebilirsiniz.
The first one is Shri Lalita, the Goddess Shri Lalita,
Bunlardan ilki Shri Lalita'dır,
which is the goddess of beauty.
güzellik tanrıçası olan Tanrıça Shri Lalita.
She is the joy giving, Sarvanandamaya.
O, neşe verendir, Sarvanandamaya.
Gives the joy from everything.
O her şeyden size neşe verir.
In every created world,
Yaratılan her dünyada,
in every particle, in every form,
her parçacıkta, her formda,
there is a power which gives us joy.
bize neşe veren bir güç vardır.
This power is the power of Shri Lalita.
Bu güç Shri Lalita'nın gücüdür.
She is called as Mahatripurasundari,
Ona Maha-tripurasundari (Üç dünyadaki en güzel kadın)  denir,
Para,  Para Atirahasya Yogini, means
Para, Para Atirahasya Yogini,
‘Para Para Atirahasya [secrets]’,
'Para Para Atirahasya [sırlar]', bu
‘the One who knows the secrets.’
bu 'sırları bilen kişi' anlamına gelir.
The ‘Para’. ‘Para’ means ‘the one that is beyond of the beyond’,
Para'. 'Para', 'ötelerinde ötesinde olan',
the secrets of that area.
o bölgenin sırları anlamına gelir.
The one who knows is Shri Lalita,
Bilen kişi,
who is the Yogini.
Yogini olan Shri Lalita'dır.
At this state She is Bindu Sarvanandamaya.
Bu konumda O, Bindu Sarvanandamaya'dır.
She is the dot [Bindu] which is joy giving.
O neşe veren noktadır [Bindu].
Second power, or ‘Avarana’ – means the enclosure-
İkinci güç ya da 'Avarana' - muhafaza anlamına gelir
is like a triangle.
– bu bir üçgen gibidir.
She is ‘Sarvasidhhipradha’.
O 'Sarvasidhhipradha'dır.
She is the One who gives all the siddhis.
O tüm siddhileri (olağanüstü güçler) verendir.
She has got three sides.
Onun üç tarafı vardır.
She [the presiding Deity] is called as Tripuramba:
O [başkanlık eden Deity] Tripuramba (büyüleyici, etkileyici, zeki) olarak adlandırılır:
Kameshwari, Vajreshvari, Bhagamalini are the three Yoginis.
Kameshwari (Arzuların Tanrısı), Vajreshvari (Yıldırım), Bhagamalini, üç Yoginidir.
Third one is called as ‘Astha Sarvarogahara’.
Üçüncüsü 'Astha Sarvarogahara' olarak adlandırılır.
This is another enclosure.
Bu başka bir muhafazadır.
The name of the Goddess is Tripurasiddha Atirahasya,
Tanrıçanın adı Tripurasiddha Atirahasya'dır,
meaning these Goddesses know the deep secrets of all the siddhis.
yani bu Tanrıçalar tüm siddhilerin derin sırlarını bilirler anlamına gelir.
The chakra is called as Sarvarogahara
Çakra, Sarvarogahara olarak adlandırılır
and the enclosure is called as Ashta.
ve muhafaza ise Ashta olarak adlandırılır.
The eight powers are called as Vagadevata,
Sekiz güç ise Vagadevata olarak adlandırılır,
means the power of the speech.
yani konuşma gücü anlamına gelir.
First is Vashini, means which attracts.
İlki Vashini, yani çeken anlamına gelir,
Kameshwari which excites.
Kameshwari, heyecanlandırır.
Modini which makes you happy.
Modini, sizi mutlu eder.
Vimala which makes you clean.
Vimala, sizi temizler.
Aruna which gives you colour of the face.
Aruna, yüzünüze renk verir.
Jayini which gives you a feeling of victory.
Jayini, size zafer hissi verir.
Sarveshi which connects you to everyone.
Sarveshi, sizi herkese bağlar.
Kaulini is the one which gives you boons.
Kaulini, size nimetler/ihsanlar verendir.
The fourth enclosure is called as ‘Antar dasha’.
Dördüncü muhafaza 'Antar dasha' olarak adlandırılır.
The chakra of this enclosure is called as Sarvarakshakari,
Bu muhafazanın çakrası Sarvarakshakari,
the One that protects.
yani koruyan olarak adlandırılır.
The Goddess is called as Tripuramalini.
Tanrıça,Tripuramalini olarak adlandırılır.
The powers are:
Güçler şunlardır:
Sarvagnya, the One which is all knowing.
Sarvagnya, her şeyi bilen.
Sarvashakti is all powerful.
Sarvashakti, her şeye gücü yeten.
Sarveshvariprada, the giver of all the bounties.
Sarveshvariprada, tüm lütufları veren.
Sarvagnyanamayi, the knower of all the knowledge.
Sarvagnyanamayi, tüm bilgileri bilen.
Sarvavyadivinashini, the destroyer of all the diseases.
Sarvavyadivinashini, tüm hastalıkların yok edicisi.
Sarvadharaswarupa, the support of all the forms.
Sarvadharaswarupa, tüm formların desteği.
Sarvapapahara, the destroyer of all the sins.
Sarvapapahara, tüm günahların yok edicisi.
Sarvanandamayi, the One who makes everyone joyous.
Sarvanandamayi, herkesi neşelendiren.
Sarvarakshaswarupini, the One who protects all of them.
Sarvarakshaswarupini, onların hepsini koruyan.
Sarvepsitaphalaprada, the giver of all the ‘phalas’,
Sarvepsitaphalaprada, tüm 'phala'ları veren,
means fruits, rewards.
yani meyveleri, ödülleri.
The fifth enclosure is called as ‘Bahir dasha Sarvartha Sadhaka’.
Beşinci muhafaza 'Bahir dasha Sarvartha Sadhaka' olarak adlandırılır.
Bahirdashar is the name of the enclosure.
Bahirdashar, muhafazanın adıdır.
And Sarvartha Sadhaka is the chakra’s name.
Sarvartha Sadhaka ise çakranın adıdır.
Tripurashri is the name of the Goddess.
Tripurashri Tanrıça'nın adıdır.
She has powers:
Onun güçleri vardır:
Sarvasiddhiprada, she gives all the siddhis.
Sarvasiddhiprada, O tüm siddhileri verir.
Sarvasampathapradha, she’s the One who’s giver of all wealth.
Sarvasampathapradha, O tüm zenginliği verendir.
Sarvapriyamkari, she’s the one who is beloved of all.
Sarvapriyamkari, O herkesin sevgilisidir.
Sarvamangalakarini, she’s the one who gives all that is auspicious.
Sarvamangalakarini, O hayırlı olan her şeyi verendir.
Sarvakamapradha, the One who gives all of our desires.
Sarvakamapradha, tüm arzularımızı veren.
Sarvadukhavimochini, the One who is the destroyer of all our pains.
Sarvadukhavimochini, tüm acılarımızın yok edicisidir.
Sarvamrityuprashamani, the One who pacifies the dead.
Sarvamrityuprashamani, ölüleri sakinleştiren.
Sarvavighnatanivarini, she is the one who is the remover of all the hurdles.
Sarvavighnatanivarini, O tüm engelleri ortadan kaldırandır.
Sarvangasundari, the One who makes every side of life happy.
Sarvangasundari, yaşamın her yanını mutlu kılandır.
Sarvasaubhagnyadayini, the One who is the giver of good fortune.
Sarvasaubhagnyadayini, iyi şans verendir.
The sixth enclosure is known as ‘Chaturdasha Sarvasaubhagnya’.
Altıncı mahfaza 'Chaturdasha Sarvasaubhagnya' olarak bilinir.
Tripuravasini is the name of the Goddess,
Tripuravasini Tanrıça'nın adıdır,
Chaturdasha is the name of the enclosure,
Chaturdasha muhafazanın adıdır
and the chakra’s name is Sarvasaubhagnyadayaka.
ve çakranın adı Sarvasaubhagnyadayaka'dır.
The Goddesses’ name is Tripuravasini.
Tanrıçanın adı Tripuravasini'dir.
The powers are:
Güçler şunlardır:
Sarvasamkshobhini, the One who burns off everything.
Sarvasamkshobhini, her şeyi yakıp yok eden.
Sarvavidravini, the One who can perverse.
Sarvavidravini, saptırabilen.
Sarvakarshini, the one which attracts everything.
Sarvakarshini, her şeyi kendine çeken.
Sarvahaladini, the One who is the giver of joy.
Sarvahaladini, neşe veren Kişi.
Sarvasammohini, the One who can entice all over.
Sarvasammohini, her şeyi baştan çıkarabilen/yol çıkarabilen.
Sarvasthambhini, the One who makes everyone alerted.
Sarvasthambhini, herkesi alarma geçiren.
Sarvajrumbhini [the power to extend].
Sarvajrumbhini, genişletme gücü.
Sarvavashamkari, the One who is the controller of all.
Sarvavashamkari, her şeyi kontrol eden olan.
Sarvaranjini, the One who entertains all.
Sarvaranjini, herkesi eğlendiren.
Sarvonmadini, She’s the one who gives all the special joys.
Sarvonmadini, tüm özel sevinçleri veren O'dur.
Sarvarthasadhini, the One who gives the meaning of all things.
Sarvarthasadhini, her şeyin anlamını veren.
Sarvasampattipurini, the One who gives all the well-being.
Sarvasampattipurini, tüm esenliği veren.
Sarvamantramayi, the one who is residing in all the mantras.
Sarvamantramayi, tüm mantraların içinde ikamet eden.
Sarvadvandvakshayankari, the one who destroys all the dualities of life.
Sarvadvandvakshayankari, yaşamın tüm ikiliklerini yok eden.
The seventh Avarana or enclosure,
Yedinci Avarana veya muhafaza,
is called as ‘Ashta dala [padma]’.
'Ashta dala [padma]' olarak adlandırılır.
And the chakra of this Avarana is called as Sarvasamkshobhanikara.
Ve bu Avarana'nın çakrası Sarvasamkshobhanikara olarak adlandırılır.
Here, She is called as Tripurasundari.
Burada O, Tripurasundari olarak adlandırılır.
She’s the one who gives the beauty to women, to be attractive wives.
O, kadınlara çekici eşler olmaları için güzellik veren kişidir.
Ananga [incorporeal] Kushuma Devi, She smells of many flowers.
Ananga [cisimsiz] Kushuma Devi, O birçok çiçek gibi kokar.
Anangamekhala Devi, who is
Anangamekhala Devi,
solid like a rock in the family.
O aile içinde bir kaya gibi sağlamdır.
Anangamadana Devi, the One who is attractive.
Anangamadana Devi, çekici olan.
Anangamadanatura Devi, the one who gives desire to meet.
Anangamadanatura Devi, Buluşma arzusu veren.
Anangarekha Devi, the One which crosses the different boundaries.
Anangarekha Devi, farklı engelleri aşan.
Anangaveghini Devi, the One which gives you speed.
Anangaveghini Devi, size konuşmayı veren.
Anangankusha Devi, the One who gives power of ‘Ankusha’,
Anangankusha Devi,  ‘Ankusha’ gücünü veren,
means the controlling of man.
bu adamı/erkeği kontrol etmek anlamına gelir.
Anangamalini Devi, the One which is very gracious.
Anangamalini Devi, çok merhametli olan.
Eighth enclosure is called as ‘Shodhasha dala [padma]’.
Sekizinci muhafaza 'Shodhasha dala [padma]' olarak adlandırılır.
The name of the chakra is Sarvashaparipuraka.
Çakranın adı Sarvashaparipuraka'dır.
The Goddesses’ name is Tripureshvari.
Tanrıçanın adı Tripureshvari'dir.
She’s the one who has got sixteen powers.
O, on altı güce sahip olandır.
The first is Kama,
İlki Kama'dır,
means the attraction [Karshini] of body.
bedenin çekiciliği [Karshini] anlamına gelir.
Buddhya is the attraction by brain.
Buddhya, beynin çekiciliğidir.
Ahamkara, attraction by ego.
Ahamkara, ego tarafından yaratılan çekim.
Fourth, Shabda, attraction by words.
Dördüncüsü Shabda, kelimelerle çekim.
Fifth is Sparsha, attraction by touch.
Beşincisi Sparsha, dokunma yoluyla çekim.
Sixth, [Rupa] attraction by beauty.
Altıncısı, [Rupa] güzellik tarafından çekim.
Seventh, attraction by aesthetics, Rasa.
Yedincisi, estetik tarafından çekim, Rasa.
Eighth, Gandha, attraction by fragrance.
Sekizincisi, Gandha, koku ile çekim.
Ninth, attraction by attention, chitta.
Dokuzuncusu, dikkat yoluyla çekim, chitta.
Tenth, Dhairya, attraction by courage.
Onuncusu, Dhairya, cesaretin çekiciliği.
Eleventh, Smritya, attraction by memory.
On birincisi, Smritya, hafıza ile çekicilik.
Twelfth, Nama, attraction by name.
On ikincisi, Nama, isimle çekim.
Thirteenth is Bija, attraction through the seed.
On üçüncüsü Bija, tohum aracılığıyla çekim.
Fourteenth, Atma, attraction by Spirit.
On dördüncüsü, Atma, Ruh tarafından çekim.
Fifteenth [Amrita] is attraction by eternity.
On beşincisi [Amrita], sonsuzluk tarafından çekim.
Sixteenth [Sharira] attraction by warmth of the body.
On altıncısı [Sharira] bedenin sıcaklığıyla çekiciliktir.
These are all the attractions which are subtle
Bunların hepsi süptil olan
and are in the Goddess,
ve Tanrıça'da bulunan,
which act in a way that
sadhaka'nın (müridinin) O'na doğru çekilmesini
the sadhaka is attracted towards Her.
sağlayacak şekilde hareket eden cazibelerdir.
The ninth one is called as the ‘Bhupura’,
Dokuzuncusu 'Bhupura' olarak adlandırılır,
this is the ninth enclosure,
bu dokuzuncu muhafazadır,
whilst chakra’s name is Trailokya Mohana.
çakranın adı ise Trailokya Mohana'dır.
The name of the Goddess is Tripura.
Tanrıça'nın adı Tripura'dır.
There are ten powers in this chakra.
Bu çakrada on güç vardır.
Its first is Sarvasankshobhini.
İlki Sarvasankshobhini'dir.
Sarva Vidravini,
Sarva Vidravini,
SavraKarshini.
SavraKarshini.
These three, I’ve already explained.
Bu üçünü zaten açıklamıştım.
Sarva Vashamkari, this one I’ve also explained.
Sarva Vashamkari, bunu da açıklamıştım.
Sarvonmadhini, the one who excites area.
Sarvonmadhini, alanı heyecanlandıran kişi.
Sarvamahankusha, the One who controls.
Sarvamahankusha, kontrol eden kişi.
Here the ‘Ankusha’ means the
Burada 'Ankusha' fil sürücüsü tarafından
weapon that is used by the elephant driver.
kullanılan silah anlamına gelir.
So, how he controls the elephant in the same way She controls all.
Sürücü fili nasıl kontrol ediyorsa, Sarvamahankusha da herkesi aynı şekilde kontrol eder.
Sarva Khechari, the One who attracts all.
Sarva Khechari, herkesi kendine çeken.
Sarva Bija, the One who is the seed in all.
Sarva Bija, her şeyin içinde tohum olan Kişi.
Sarva Yoni, the One who exists in all the yonis.
Sarva Yoni, tüm yonilerde var olan.
And Sarvatrikhanda, the One which exists in all the three dimensions
Ve Sarvatrikhanda, her üç boyutta da var olan
‘Yoni’ means ‘the ellipse’ which is the power of the Mother.
'Yoni'  Anne'nin gücü olan 'elips' anlamına gelir.
Apart from that, there are other Goddesses,
Bunun dışında, Muktashaktayama olarak bilinen sarı çizgi olarak
which exist as the yellow line known as Muktashaktayama
var olan başka Tanrıçalar da vardır
The Mother Goddesses are called as Mahendri, Chamunda and Mahalakshmi.
Ana Tanrıçalar Mahendri, Chamunda ve Mahalakshmi olarak adlandırılır.
The siddhis that people can achieve are: Anima,
İnsanların ulaşabileceği siddhiler şunlardır: Anima,
Laghima, Mahima, Ishitva, Vashistva, Prakamya,
Laghima, Mahima, Ishitva, Vashistva, Prakamya,
Bhukti, Iccha, Prapti, Mukti.
Bhukti, Iccha, Prapti, Mukti.
Anima is to become like a small particle.
Anima küçük bir parçacık gibi olmaktır.
Laghima is to become small.
Laghima küçük olmaktır.
Mahima is to have a big form.
Mahima büyük bir forma sahip olmaktır.
Ishitva is to create gods out of human beings.
Ishitva insanlardan tanrılar yaratmaktır.
Vashistva is the attraction.
Vashistva çekiciliktir.
Prakamya is the manifestation.
Prakamya tezahürdür.
Bhukti is the enjoyment.
Bhukti, keyif almaktır.
[Iccha is] the fulfilment of desire.
Iccha, arzunun yerine getirilmesidir.
Prapti is the attainment.
Prapti, ulaşmaktır.
Mukti is the salvation.
Mukti, kurtuluştur.
These are all the siddhis that Sahaja Yogis can have.
Bunlar Sahaja Yogilerin sahip olabileceği tüm siddhilerdir.